Guide to the Sewanee Controversy Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Sewanee Controversy Papers
1867-1988
RG 186
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(4 boxes)
The Sewanee Controversy Papers include the official documents surrounding the event, as well as personal correspondence and collected material. From 1952 to 1954 there was great controversy over the admission policies of the School of Theology at the University of the South at Sewanee, an Episcopal Seminary. On June 6, 1952, the Board of Trustees rejected a request by the Synod of the Fourth Province to "open the existing seminaries in the South to students of all races." The Board of Trustees concluded that "the admission of Negroes, or men of any other race...is inadvisable." This resolution sparked a flurry of responses, most notably the resignation of eight faculty members in protest. In June 1953, the Board of Trustees voted to change its policy.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of R. Lansing Hicks.
Biographical / Historical
1950, Jan 25 Francis Craighill Brown installed as Dean of the School of Theology at the University of the South (Sewanee)
1952, June Sewanee Board of Trustees rejects proposal to admit African American students. Eight faculty members protest, threatening to resign by June, 1953, unless the decision isoverturned.
1952, November The eight faculty members resign, effective June, 1953.
1953, January Bishop Daindridge is elected Sewanee's new dean, 4 other new faculty members are appointed
1953, February Rev. Dr. James Pike declines to speak at Sewanee's graduation ceremony because of its admission policies.
1953, June Board of Trustees votes to disregard race in considering applicants. First African-American student is admitted at Sewanee.
Scope and Contents
The Papers include the official documents surrounding the controversy, as well as personal correspondence and collected material. The material dates primarily from 1952 to 1954, although there is some material from before and after that timeframe. The collection provides valuable documentation of a specific instance of racial discrimination in the American South during the early 1950s.
Series I contains relevant official documents about the events including Proceedings and Reports of the Board of Trustees and Board of Regents, faculty responses, and other statements. It also includes documents that refer to the wider discussion of the controversy, including statements of support from universities and students, discussions of the issue, miscellaneous notes, and background. The papers address the controversy of 1952-1953 but also include papers about the following school year, including remarks by students. It also includes a few historical accounts, including a thorough history called the "Sewanee Story."
Series II contains relevant correspondence about the Sewanee events. The bulk of the correspondence was written to and from Dean F. Craighill Brown on behalf of the faculty. Most are letters of support. The response to some of the letters to Brown/faculty were written by other members of the faculty, notably R. Lansing Hicks (who was later on the faculty at Berkeley Divinity School and Yale Divinity School and from whom these papers were received by the Library.) Where possible and logical, the correspondence of specific individuals has been sorted out of this collection, including correspondence of Bishop R. Bland Mitchell, Morgan Cartledge Williams (a trustee), Vice-Chancellor McCrady, C.F. Peniman, and Bishop Edwin Penick. The responses of Members of the Board of Trustees in June and July of 1952 are separated out from the rest of the correspondence to Dean Brown. Series II also contains the correspondence of Professors R.Lansing Hicks, Richard Hooker Wilmer, and. Thomas Govan, a professor of History at Sewanee. This series also contains letters of student support and correspondence about media coverage of the events.
Series III contains Collected Material from a variety of sources. Most of the articles/clippings were collected by R.Lansing Hicks and Dean F. Craighill Brown. They are in chronological order and span from 1950-1954. There are also complete journals and publications from the same time span, including the Episcopal Church News, The Living Church, The Sewanee Alumni News, and The Theo-log. There is also a large article from the New Oxford Review about Bishop Pike from 1976.
Arrangement
I. Documents, 1867-1988
II. Correspondence, 1949-1954
III. Collected Material, 1950-1976
African Americans -- Education (Higher); United States -- Race relations; Episcopal Church ( Education); University of the South. School of Theology -- History
- Documents, 1867-1988; Series I
  - Lambeth Conferences on Race; and Documents about racial issues at Sewanee predating June, 1952, 1867-1948, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Proceedings of the Board of Trustees, Board of Trustees Resolutions, 1952, June 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Response; Statement by Bishop Mitchell, Vice Chancellor McCrady's Response, Faculty Statement of Clarification, June 9-21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Is There a Race Problem at the University of the South?" an open letter by Prof Kayden and responses, 1952, June 18 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "What is the Issue at Sewanee?"; notes on discrimination, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of Regents, reports, 1952, July 31, Oct 8-10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Faculty resignation and related correspondence, 1952, Oct (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recommendation of the 4th Province Synod and Vice Chancellor McCrady's response, 1952, Nov (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Statements of support from other colleges, seminaries and divinity schools., 1952, fall (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Statements of student support, 1952, fall (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "The Troubles ot Sewanee", Rev. Bayard H. Jones (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Report of the Special Committee of the Board of Trustees; Report of the Vice-Chancellor to the Board of Trustees, 1953, May, June (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "The Sewanee Story", 1953, March (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Milton Crum's notes on summer school of Theology; compilation of student/faculty impressions of Sewanee, 1953,1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sewanee Class roster, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Proceedings of the Board of Trustees, 1954, June (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Action of the 140th Convention of the Diocese of North Carolina, 1956, May 9 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letter with history from Wayne Holman to Hicks; "20th century witchhunt" by Francis Russell, 1984, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Information about the collection of the Sewanee papers (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1949-1954; Series II
  - Correspondence of Dean F. Craighill Brown/Faculty, 1952, June (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence of Dean F. Craighill Brown/Faculty, 1952, July-Oct (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence of Dean F. Craighill Brown/Faculty with Trustees/Board of Regents, 1952, June-Oct (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence of Dean F. Craighill Brown/Faculty, 1952, November (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence of Dean F. Craighill Brown/Faculty, 1952, Dec to 1953, Jan (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence of Dean F. Craighill Brown/Faculty, 1953, Feb-March (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence of Dean F. Craighill Brown/Faculty, 1953, April - 1954 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence with Bishop R. Bland Mitchell, 1952, June - 1953, Jan (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence with Morgan Cartledge Williams ("Quill"), a trustee, 1952, Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence between Dean F. Craighill Brown and Vice-Chancellor Ed McCrady, 1952, Fall (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Letter from Dean Pike to McCrady, 1953, Feb 10 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence between F.C. Brown, Arthur Walmsley and Dean McCrady, 1953, March (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence of C.F. Penniman, 1952, Fall (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence with Bishop Edwin Penick (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence re: journalism/articles, 1949-1953 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Letters of student support (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence of R. Lansing Hicks, 1952, Jun-Oct (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence of R. Lansing Hicks, 1952, Nov -1954 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence between C. Breck Wilmer, Professor Kayden, and Richard H. Wilmer, 1952, Jun-Dec (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Personal correspondence of R.H. Wilmer and Bishop Danridge, 1952, June-Dec (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence of Rev. Richard Hooker Wilmer, 1951 - June, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence of Rev. Richard Hooker Wilmer, 1952, July-Dec (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence of Rev. Richard Hooker Wilmer, 1953, Jan-1954 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Letter from Thomas Govan (History professor) to Clifford Morehouse (editor of the Living Church and president of Morehouse-Gordham Public College), 1952, Nov (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Biography of Thomas Govan (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Other miscellaneous correspondence (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Collected Material, 1950-1976; Series III
  - Articles, 1950 - 1953, Feb (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Articles, 1953, Mar - 1954 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Articles (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - The Episcopal Church News, 1952, Jun- 1953, Jun (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - The Living Church, 1952, Jun- 1953, Feb (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Sewanee Alumni News, 1952, Aug- 1953, Aug (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - The Theo-log, 1953, Mar-Dec (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Article in the New Oxford Review: "The Death and Life of Bishop Pike", 1976 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Miscellaneous collected material (Box 4, Folder 55)